Farewell, Earth
The ship that is departing is
The Space Battleship
Yamato
It departs now to Iscandar,
at the end of the cosmos,
bearing its fate.
"We will come back, no matter what it takes"
Answer with a smile to the waving people
Going far from the Galaxy towards Iscandar
A faint gleam of hope
The Space Battleship Yamato
Pluto
Gamilas Pluto Forward Base
The Teron ship made a hyperspace jump?
And they destroyed the resupply base? Have you gone mad?
But, Commander Goer... It's clear they broke the light-speed barrier?
Silence!
Do you really think a commander in charge of a galactic theater,
can report such nonsense to imperial command?
Shultz!
I shall only be able to report to our lord after you've provided a proper report.
You understand what I'm asking, yes?
Yes, sir.
If so, I'll speak to command about promoting all of you
from second-class Gamilans to first-class.
Got it? I want a proper report, Shultz!
He doesn't understand anything...
Show me the Zupist footage.
Here's the issue. What could have done this?
What could even make something like this possible?
The flight plan the UN's Yamato Plan HQ made does not allow for any lost time at Pluto.
In other words, any decision about carrying out Operation M-2 has been left to us.
We should do it!
We should disable the Pluto base, if only to prevent any troubles with it later.
Navigation Officer, your opinion?
I believe this to be our fastest course out of the solar system.
Meaning that...
Wait... Following that course, we'll pass Pluto without mounting any attack.
I understand how you feel.
However, our flight plan has no leeway.
But...
Report from the main bridge. We've picked up a distress call.
UN Cosmo Force Standard Code. Very weak.
What's the ship's name?
We can't tell. It's coming from
the vicinity of the south pole of Enceladus, one of Saturn's moons.
Saturn, huh? The opposite direction from Pluto.
And from the course you plotted, too.
Assuming we go to Enceladus, how many days are lost?
Two.
Here is my opinion, as the Tactical Officer:
We shouldn't lose time here.
What are you talking about, Kodai?
A sailor can't abandon another sailor!
Since we're unsure there even are survivors, we shouldn't squander valuable time!
Is that not what you just said?
Right now, our priority...
...is to reach Iscandar. Not to destroy the Pluto base.
Even if the chance of survivors is minuscule, we should go.
What?
Engine room, status report.
This is bad... Part of the condenser is on the verge of melting.
We closed the safety valve, right?
Yes, the emergency breaker apparently didn't activate.
If we do nothing, it could paralyze the ship.
How long will repairs take?
That isn't an easy question. To repair it, we'd need to...
Cosmonite 90?
It's a rare material required to repair the condenser.
Hirata, do we have any on board?
Not nearly enough for the repairs.
There! I found it.
Enceladus has an abandoned
cosmonite mine. We can resupply there.
Change course. Head for Enceladus.
However, recovering the cosmonite is our priority. Understood?
Yes, sir.
The Teron ship has changed course?
Our recon ships show them heading toward the sixth planet, Zedan.
Jarletora, wasn't a recon landing ship stationed near Zedan?
Yes.
Use that. Take prisoners if possible.
I want to know what they're up to.
The OMCS is amazing. It can make as much of this food as you want.
But what does it use for raw material?
Don't ask hard questions, Aihara.
Huh? That's all you want, Sanada?
Yeah. Consuming unnecessary calories is foolish.
Um, Sanada, what does the OMCS use to make the food?
I think you're better off not knowing.
May I sit here?
Sure.
I'm not against the rescue operation itself. Just...
You lost your brother on Pluto.
I understand your desire to redress that.
Actually, I'm the same way...
My dad was a sailor. And he always used to say...
Listen, Daisuke.
Sailors like your dad never abandon their comrades, no matter what.
That's what it means to be a sailor... A true sailor.
I wanted to be like him. That's why I became a sailor.
They're such good friends.
Both were promoted because those who would have had their jobs got killed.
Aren't they lucky?
It's a friendship between men.
No, I mean...
They're just simple.
They're just self-absorbed. You shouldn't try to emulate them.
Right! Understood!
After inspection, team 5 is to gather in the briefing room.
Repeat.
We will discuss our maintenance and operation plans.
Inertial control isn't on in here, right?
There's so much stuff in here...
We're better off without gravity.
So, what is it?
Permission was granted for the extra ammunition you requested.
Thanks.
How's the accounting going?
Fine. I'm enjoying it.
<Target approaching orbit of the eighth satellite.>
<Command priority: capture of crew.>
<Weapons use permitted, as necessary.>
It looks like a messed-up golf ball.
On that frozen surface, we've seen geysers
caused by the tidal pull from Saturn and other planets.
Landing on Enceladus.
Begin descent.
Approach angle is fine. Forward at minimum speed.
Red 15, descent angle 16.
Lower bow, and prepare for docking.
All ready.
XO Sanada, you're in charge of the mining site.
Yes, sir.
Operations Officer Mori.
Take Analyzer and a medical team to the distress signal's source.
See if there is anyone you can help.
Yes, sir.
Kodai, you are to escort Mori.
Um, what do you mean?
I believe you are to protect her.
No, that won't be necessary.
What a treasure trove...
Boatswain, complete the work as fast as you can.
Aye aye, sir.
So I guess Kodai's off to escort the princess.
In training school, I was his instructor.
He never did know how to deal with women.
I wonder if he'll be all right...
Two girls and a robot alone?
Don't worry.
You won't need to do a thing.
I am quite capable. You may leave it to me.
Glad to hear it.
Glad to hear it indeed.
I'll leave the escort to you.
But on the ground, you obey my orders.
Right, right.
One "right"  is enough.
Hey...
Hey, aren't those two kind of suspicious together?
I detect no suspicious activity.
You're such a bore.
But this distress signal... Who could have sent it?
What?
Could I ask a strange question?
I guess...
I was right!
Are you related to any aliens?
Am I what?
No, never mind. Forget it.
Now approaching signal source.
This is definitely an Earth ship.
With that conning tower, it's probably...
An Isokaze-class assault destroyer.
The same type as the Yukikaze.
It's frozen over, so I can't read the ship's name.
Mori! Kodai!
We can enter over here!
This is the only system still working. It's transmitting the distress call.
Yeah.
I'll look around a little more.
Okay, I'll find the ship's log.
Okay, thanks.
It's no good...
Gamilans!
They got the seagull!
Did something happen?
You request help from the Yamato.
Understood.
Harada!
I'm locked in!
Open, damn you!
This is the medical team. Yamato, please respond.
It's no use...
Analyzer, weren't you going to help?
Due to emergency circumstances, I'm transmitting unencrypted.
We are currently under Gamilas attack.
We require immediate assistance!
This is the Yamato!
We are currently under attack by an enemy armored units.
Hit to starboard! Damage minimal!
Do you copy, medical team?
Engine is off line, so both main and secondary guns are dead.
Fighters are to launch and engage the enemy.
Repeat, fighters are to launch...
Withdraw! Withdraw immediately!
Idiots!
They don't have nearly the forces to attack the Yamato.
Yup.
Okay, just like that.
So you're useful, after all.
Of course.
This is strange.
They've stopped attacking.
Kodai, the Yamato is also under fire!
We can't launch?
We're still recovering the dig team!
If you want to launch from here, we'll need to gain altitude.
Hold on...
Then what should we do?
I guess we'll borrow it.
"It"?
Hey!
Did they issue launch orders?
Hey, who's in that thing?
It isn't one of the pilots?
Hey! You there! State your name and rank!
I don't know who you are, but go assist the medical team!
This is the medical team. Yamato, please respond!
Medical team, do you copy?
On my way now.
Okay!
You did it!
Mori!
<Take her to the tank.>
Kodai!
Stay down!
The first aid box!
That's an enemy.
It doesn't matter!
Take this, Gammy!
Darn!
Kodai!
Run!
Get down!
Pretty impressive.
Yeah.
Thank you. You saved me.
This thing saved me.
What's wrong?
Hey! What's wrong?
This was my brother's...
Mamoru
Kodai
This was my brother's ship.
It was my brother's Yukikaze!
Yukikaze
Remove your helmet.
Jeez... I should have known.
Huh?
Where's the tactical officer?
Kodai is giving his report.
You don't need to go?
Reporting.
Origin of distress call was the destroyer Yukikaze, of the UN Cosmo Force First Fleet.
There were no survivors on board...
No survivors, huh?
Kodai.
We don't want the Earth to end up like the Yukikaze, do we?
No, we don't.
Here lie the twenty-four brave souls who crewed the Yukikaze.
May they rest in peace.
Episode 4
Gravestone on a Frozen Field
The unknown calls to us
Does your courage burn to go there?
We rush on a journey
For everyone to survive together
For happiness
Though there is pain
And sadness
We will not be defeated
Those who know the beautiful Earth
Restore its wonders
Bring it back, bring it back
The road to tomorrow
Not afraid anymore
Determined to reach our destination
The planet with the king of the dead's name stands before the Yamato.
Unless the planet is overcome, humanity has no future.
All crew, battle stations! Our target is Pluto!
Can the Yamato break through the trap that lies in wait?
The biggest battle of the solar system begins now.
Next time: The Trap on All Sides.
There are 362 days left before humanity is extinct.